<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cve_news</title>
    <link>https://www.cve.org/Media/News/AllNews</link>
    <description>Latest posts from https://www.cve.org/Media/News/AllNews</description>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <generator>python-feedgen</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 09:14:05 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <title>Vulnerability Data Enrichment for CVE Records: 217 CNAs on the Enrichment Recognition List for October 7, 2024</title>
      <link>https://www.cve.org/Media/News/item/blog/2024/10/08/CNA-Enrichment-Recognition-List-Update</link>
      <description>The “CNA Enrichment Recognition List” for October 7, 2024, is now available with 217 CNAs listed. Published every two weeks on the CVE website, the list recognizes thoseCVE Numbering Authorities (CNAs)that are actively providing enhanced vulnerability data in theirCVE Records. CNAs are added to the list if they provideCommon Vulnerability Scoring System (CVSS)andCommon Weakness Enumeration (CWE™)information 98% of the time or more within the two-week period of their last published CVE Record.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Minutes from CVE Board Teleconference Meeting on October 2 Now Available</title>
      <link>https://www.cve.org/Media/News/item/news/2024/10/15/CVE-Board-Minutes-from-October-2</link>
      <description>TheCVE Boardheld a teleconference meeting on October 2, 2024. Read themeeting minutes summary.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CVE Program Adds New “CVE Artificial Intelligence Working Group (CVEAI WG)”</title>
      <link>https://www.cve.org/Media/News/item/news/2024/10/15/New-CVE-Artificial-Intelligence-Working-Group</link>
      <description>The CVE Program’s newest working group (WG),CVE Artificial Intelligence(CVEAI WG), is open to CVE community members such asCVE Numbering Authorities (CNAs), theCVE Board,Authorized Data Publishers (ADPs), and participants from theCVE Program Secretariat; members of corporate vulnerability management programs and related standards, initiatives, and associations; and members of the AI community with expertise in AI and AI-related security concerns.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Call for Papers Now Open forCVE/FIRST VulnCon 2025on April 7-10, 2025</title>
      <link>https://www.cve.org/Media/News/item/blog/2024/10/22/Call-for-Papers-Now-Open-for-VulnCon</link>
      <description>TheCVE ProgramandFIRSTwill co-hostVulnCon 2025at the McKimmon Center in Raleigh, North Carolina, USA, on April 7-10, 2025. TheCall for Papersis open until January 15, 2025. See detailshere.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Our CVE Story: Biohacking Village</title>
      <link>https://www.cve.org/Media/News/item/blog/2024/10/22/Our-CVE-Story-Biohacking-Village</link>
      <description>Guest authors Janine (Nina Alli) and Jennifer Agüero are both from Biohacking Village. Janine is CEO/Executive Director and Jennifer is a Marketing Communications Specialist. Biohacking Village is a CVE Numbering Authority (CNA) partner under the CISA ICS Root.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vulnerability Data Enrichment for CVE Records: 221 CNAs on the Enrichment Recognition List for October 21, 2024</title>
      <link>https://www.cve.org/Media/News/item/blog/2024/10/22/CNA-Enrichment-Recognition-List-Update</link>
      <description>The “CNA Enrichment Recognition List” for October 21, 2024, is now available with 221 CNAs listed. Published every two weeks on the CVE website, the list recognizes thoseCVE Numbering Authorities (CNAs)that are actively providing enhanced vulnerability data in theirCVE Records. CNAs are added to the list if they provideCommon Vulnerability Scoring System (CVSS)andCommon Weakness Enumeration (CWE™)information 98% of the time or more within the two-week period of their last published CVE Record.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PingCAP Added as CVE Numbering Authority (CNA)</title>
      <link>https://www.cve.org/Media/News/item/news/2024/10/22/PingCAP-Added-as-CNA</link>
      <description>PingCAP (US), Inc.is now aCVE Numbering Authority (CNA)for vulnerabilities in the following PingCAP maintained products and components: TiDB (code available athttps://github.com/pingcap/tidb); TiKV (code available athttps://github.com/tikv/tikv); PD (Placement Driver, code available athttps://github.com/tikv/pd); TiFlash (code available athttps://github.com/pingcap/tiflash); and tidbcloud (PingCAP’s cloud database service). This scope includes vulnerabilities in all supported versions of these products. CVE IDs will not be assigned for vulnerabilities found in unsupported versions or for third-party dependencies not maintained by PingCAP.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>OMRON Added as CVE Numbering Authority (CNA)</title>
      <link>https://www.cve.org/Media/News/item/news/2024/10/22/OMRON-Added-as-CNA</link>
      <description>OMRON Corporationis now aCVE Numbering Authority (CNA)for Omron Group companies’ Industrial Automation, Healthcare, Social Systems, Device &amp; Module Solutions issues only.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cyber Security Agency of Singapore Added as CVE Numbering Authority (CNA)</title>
      <link>https://www.cve.org/Media/News/item/news/2024/10/22/Cyber-Security-Agency-of-Singapore-Added-as</link>
      <description>Cyber Security Agency of Singapore(CSA) is now aCVE Numbering Authority (CNA)for vulnerabilities reported to CSA unless covered by the scope of another CNA.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CVE Program Celebrates 25 Years of Impact!</title>
      <link>https://www.cve.org/Media/News/item/blog/2024/10/22/CVE-Program-Celebrates-25-Years</link>
      <description>Today, theCommon Vulnerabilities and Exposures (CVE®) Programproudly commemorates its25th anniversary, marking a quarter-century of enabling coordinated vulnerability management through global collaboration and innovation. Launched in 1999, the CVE Program has transformed the way organizations identify and manage cybersecurity vulnerabilities, enabling stronger defenses against cyber threats. TheCVE 25th Anniversary Reportis available now on the CVE.ORG website.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
