<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cve_news</title>
    <link>https://www.cve.org/Media/News/AllNews</link>
    <description>Latest posts from https://www.cve.org/Media/News/AllNews. follow.is: feedId:72158581942748160+userId:71370844472670208</description>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <generator>python-feedgen</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 24 Feb 2025 01:38:38 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <title>MegaZone Reelected as CNA Liaison Board Member</title>
      <link>https://www.cve.org/Media/News/item/news/2025/02/11/MegaZone-Reelected-CNA-Liaison-Board-Member</link>
      <description>MegaZone Reelected as CNA Liaison Board MembernewsFebruary 11, 2025TheCVE Programis pleased to announce that MegaZone ofF5, Inc.received the majority of votes from CNAs and was reelected as theCVE Numbering Authority (CNA)Liaison to theCVE Boardfor another one-year term.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vulnerability Data Enrichment for CVE Records: 241 CNAs on the Enrichment Recognition List for February 10, 2025</title>
      <link>https://www.cve.org/Media/News/item/blog/2025/02/11/CNA-Enrichment-Recognition-List-Update</link>
      <description>Vulnerability Data Enrichment for CVE Records: 241 CNAs on the Enrichment Recognition List for February 10, 2025blogBy CVE Program|February 11, 2025The “CNA Enrichment Recognition List” for February 10, 2025, is now available with 241 CNAs listed. Published every two weeks on the CVE website, the list recognizes thoseCVE Numbering Authorities (CNAs)that are actively providing enhanced vulnerability data in theirCVE Records. CNAs are added to the list if they provideCommon Vulnerability Scoring System (CVSS)andCommon Weakness Enumeration (CWE™)information 98% of the time or more within the two-week period of their last published CVE Record.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Securepoint Added as CVE Numbering Authority (CNA)</title>
      <link>https://www.cve.org/Media/News/item/news/2025/02/11/Securepoint-Added-as-CNA</link>
      <description>Securepoint Added as CVE Numbering Authority (CNA)newsFebruary 11, 2025Securepoint GmbHis now aCVE Numbering Authority (CNA)for Securepoint GmbH issues only.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Centreon Added as CVE Numbering Authority (CNA)</title>
      <link>https://www.cve.org/Media/News/item/news/2025/02/11/Centreon-Added-as-CNA</link>
      <description>Centreon Added as CVE Numbering Authority (CNA)newsFebruary 11, 2025Centreonis now aCVE Numbering Authority (CNA)for all Centreon product issues only.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ATISoluciones Added as CVE Numbering Authority (CNA)</title>
      <link>https://www.cve.org/Media/News/item/news/2025/02/11/ATISoluciones-Added-as-CNA</link>
      <description>ATISoluciones Added as CVE Numbering Authority (CNA)newsFebruary 11, 2025ATISoluciones Diseño de Sistemas Electrónicos, S.L.is now aCVE Numbering Authority (CNA)for AtiSoluciones products only.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Minutes from CVE Board Teleconference Meeting on January 22 Now Available</title>
      <link>https://www.cve.org/Media/News/item/news/2025/02/18/CVE-Board-Minutes-from-January-22</link>
      <description>Minutes from CVE Board Teleconference Meeting on January 22 Now AvailablenewsFebruary 18, 2025TheCVE Boardheld a teleconference meeting on January 22, 2025. Read themeeting minutes summary.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pangea Cyber Added as CVE Numbering Authority (CNA)</title>
      <link>https://www.cve.org/Media/News/item/news/2025/02/18/Pangea-Cyber-Added-as-CNA</link>
      <description>Pangea Cyber Added as CVE Numbering Authority (CNA)newsFebruary 18, 2025Pangea Cyber Corporationis now aCVE Numbering Authority (CNA)for all Pangea Cyber products and services, as well as vulnerabilities in third-party software that are not in another CNA’s scope.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Softing Added as CVE Numbering Authority (CNA)</title>
      <link>https://www.cve.org/Media/News/item/news/2025/02/18/Softing-Added-as-CNA</link>
      <description>Softing Added as CVE Numbering Authority (CNA)newsFebruary 18, 2025Softingis now aCVE Numbering Authority (CNA)for Softing issues only.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Danfoss Added as CVE Numbering Authority (CNA)</title>
      <link>https://www.cve.org/Media/News/item/news/2025/02/18/Danfoss-Added-as-CNA</link>
      <description>Danfoss Added as CVE Numbering Authority (CNA)newsFebruary 18, 2025Danfossis now aCVE Numbering Authority (CNA)for Danfoss products only.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CVE ID Assignment and CVE Record Publication for AI-Related Vulnerabilities</title>
      <link>https://www.cve.org/Media/News/item/blog/2025/02/18/CVE-ID-CVE-Record-AIrelated-Vulnerabilities</link>
      <description>CVE ID Assignment and CVE Record Publication for AI-Related VulnerabilitiesblogBy CVE Program|February 18, 2025This is the second blog in a CVE Program AI Blog SeriesThis series is documenting the journey theCVE Boardis on determining how to addressvulnerabilitiesin a CVE context. It is the intent of theCVE Programto be transparent with our thinking and general guidance as we investigate the impact to CVE efforts and establish swim lanes for CVE assignments in an AI-enabled world.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
