<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cve_news</title>
    <link>https://www.cve.org/Media/News/AllNews</link>
    <description>Latest posts from https://www.cve.org/Media/News/AllNews. follow.is: feedId:72158581942748160+userId:71370844472670208</description>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <generator>python-feedgen</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 07 Mar 2025 01:39:04 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <title>Softing Added as CVE Numbering Authority (CNA)</title>
      <link>https://www.cve.org/Media/News/item/news/2025/02/18/Softing-Added-as-CNA</link>
      <description>Softing Added as CVE Numbering Authority (CNA)newsFebruary 18, 2025Softingis now aCVE Numbering Authority (CNA)for Softing issues only.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Danfoss Added as CVE Numbering Authority (CNA)</title>
      <link>https://www.cve.org/Media/News/item/news/2025/02/18/Danfoss-Added-as-CNA</link>
      <description>Danfoss Added as CVE Numbering Authority (CNA)newsFebruary 18, 2025Danfossis now aCVE Numbering Authority (CNA)for Danfoss products only.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CVE ID Assignment and CVE Record Publication for AI-Related Vulnerabilities</title>
      <link>https://www.cve.org/Media/News/item/blog/2025/02/18/CVE-ID-CVE-Record-AIrelated-Vulnerabilities</link>
      <description>CVE ID Assignment and CVE Record Publication for AI-Related VulnerabilitiesblogBy CVE Program|February 18, 2025This is the second blog in a CVE Program AI Blog Series. The first blog in the series, “CVE and AI-related Vulnerabilities,” is availablehere.This series is documenting the journey theCVE Boardis on determining how to addressvulnerabilitiesin a CVE context. It is the intent of theCVE Programto be transparent with our thinking and general guidance as we investigate the impact to CVE efforts and establish swim lanes for CVE assignments in an AI-enabled world.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CVE Program Report for Quarter 4 Calendar Year (Q4 CY) 2024</title>
      <link>https://www.cve.org/Media/News/item/blog/2025/02/25/CVE-Program-Report-for-Q4-2024</link>
      <description>CVE Program Report for Quarter 4 Calendar Year (Q4 CY) 2024blogBy CVE Program|February 25, 2025The CVE Program’s quarterly summary of program milestones and metrics for Q4 CY 2024.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vulnerability Data Enrichment for CVE Records: 240 CNAs on the Enrichment Recognition List for February 24, 2025</title>
      <link>https://www.cve.org/Media/News/item/blog/2025/02/25/CNA-Enrichment-Recognition-List-Update</link>
      <description>Vulnerability Data Enrichment for CVE Records: 240 CNAs on the Enrichment Recognition List for February 24, 2025blogBy CVE Program|February 25, 2025</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Saviynt Added as CVE Numbering Authority (CNA)</title>
      <link>https://www.cve.org/Media/News/item/news/2025/02/25/Saviynt-Added-as-CNA</link>
      <description>Saviynt Added as CVE Numbering Authority (CNA)newsFebruary 25, 2025Saviynt Inc.is now aCVE Numbering Authority (CNA)for vulnerabilities discovered in Saviynt products or vulnerabilities reported to Saviynt Labs that are not in another CNA’s scope. Read theSaviynt press release.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CPAN Security Group Added as CVE Numbering Authority (CNA)</title>
      <link>https://www.cve.org/Media/News/item/news/2025/02/25/CPAN-Security-Group-Added-as-CNA</link>
      <description>CPAN Security Group Added as CVE Numbering Authority (CNA)newsFebruary 25, 2025CPAN Security Groupis now aCVE Numbering Authority (CNA)for vulnerabilities in Perl and CPAN Modules (including End-of-Life Perl versions) found athttps://perl.org,https://cpan.org, orhttps://metacpan.org/, excluding distributions of Perl or CPAN Modules maintained by third-party redistributors.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Red Hat Adds a CNA of Last Resort (CNA-LR) to its Root Hierarchy</title>
      <link>https://www.cve.org/Media/News/item/blog/2025/02/25/Red-Hat-Root-Adds-CNA-LR</link>
      <description>Red Hat Adds a CNA of Last Resort (CNA-LR) to its Root HierarchyblogBy CVE Program|February 25, 2025TheCVE Programis pleased to announce that theRed Hat Roothas now established a “CVE Numbering Authority of Last Resort (CNA-LR)” to assignCVE Identifiers (CVE IDs)and to publish correspondingCVE Recordsfor vulnerabilities in software developed by aCNAwithin the Red Hat Root hierarchy. As a Root, “Red Hat’s scope includes the open source community. Any open source organizations that prefer Red Hat as their Root; organizations are free to choose another Root if it suits them better.”</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Minutes from CVE Board Teleconference Meeting on February 5 Now Available</title>
      <link>https://www.cve.org/Media/News/item/news/2025/03/04/CVE-Board-Minutes-from-February-5</link>
      <description>Minutes from CVE Board Teleconference Meeting on February 5 Now AvailablenewsMarch 4, 2025TheCVE Boardheld a teleconference meeting on February 5, 2025. Read themeeting minutes summary.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Please Complete Our “CVE Data Usage and Satisfaction Survey” by April 4, 2025</title>
      <link>https://www.cve.org/Media/News/item/blog/2025/03/04/CVE-Data-Usage-and-Satisfaction-Survey</link>
      <description>Please Complete Our “CVE Data Usage and Satisfaction Survey” by April 4, 2025blogBy CVE Program|March 4, 2025TheCVE Programis continuously investigating new methods and offerings that will better inform the overall community regarding publicly disclosed vulnerabilities. To that end, we would greatly appreciate your feedback to our “CVE Data Usage and Satisfaction Survey.” The survey opens today and will close at 11:59 PM ET on April 4, 2025.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
