<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>deeplearning</title>
    <link>https://www.deeplearning.ai/the-batch/</link>
    <description>Latest posts from https://www.deeplearning.ai/the-batch/. follow.is: None</description>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <generator>python-feedgen</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 15 Mar 2025 01:38:18 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <title>DeepSeek Takes On OpenAI, Robots Fold Laundry, Amazon and Anthropic Expand Partnership, More Efficient Object Detection</title>
      <link>https://www.deeplearning.ai/the-batch/issue-277/</link>
      <description>The Batch AI News and Insights: DeepSeek Takes On OpenAI, Robots Fold Laundry, Amazon and Anthropic Expand Partnership, More Efficient Object Detection.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AI Agents Spend Real Money, Breaking Jailbreaks, Mistral Goes Big and Multimodal, AI’s Growing E-Waste Problem</title>
      <link>https://www.deeplearning.ai/the-batch/issue-278/</link>
      <description>The Batch AI News and Insights: AI Agents Spend Real Money, Breaking Jailbreaks, Mistral Goes Big and Multimodal, AI’s Growing E-Waste Problem.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Amazon Nova’s Competitive Price/Performance, OpenAI o1 Pro’s High Price/Performance, Google’s Game Worlds on Tap, Factual LLMs</title>
      <link>https://www.deeplearning.ai/the-batch/issue-279/</link>
      <description>The Batch AI News and Insights: AI Product Management is evolving rapidly. The growth of generative AI and AI-based developer tools has created numerous opportunities to build AI applications.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phi-4 Breaks Size Barrier, HunyuanVideo Narrows Open Source Gap, Gemini 2.0 Flash Accelerates Multimodal Modeling, LLMs Propose Research Ideas</title>
      <link>https://www.deeplearning.ai/the-batch/issue-280/</link>
      <description>The Batch AI News and Insights: I’m thrilled that former students and postdocs of mine won both of this year’s NeurIPS Test of Time Paper Awards.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Top AI Stories of 2024! Agents Rise, Prices Fall, Models Shrink, Video Takes Off, Acquisitions Morph</title>
      <link>https://www.deeplearning.ai/the-batch/issue-281/</link>
      <description>The Batch AI News and Insights: Is AI progressing rapidly? Yes! But while the progress of underlying AI technology has indeed sped up over the past 2 years, the fastest acceleration is in applications.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Happy New Year! Hopes For 2025 With Mustafa Suleyman, Audrey Tang, Albert Gu, Hanno Basse, Joseph Gonzalez, David Ding</title>
      <link>https://www.deeplearning.ai/the-batch/issue-282/</link>
      <description>The Batch AI News and Insights: Despite having worked on AI since I was a teenager, I’m now more excited than ever about what we can do with it, especially in building AI applications.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>When Good Models Do Bad Things, What Users Really Want, More Training Data!, Better Model Merging</title>
      <link>https://www.deeplearning.ai/the-batch/issue-283/</link>
      <description>The Batch AI News and Insights: Using AI-assisted coding to build software prototypes is an important way to quickly explore many ideas and invent new things.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tumbling Training Costs, Desktop AI Supercomputer, Tighter AI Export Restrictions, Improved Contrastive Loss</title>
      <link>https://www.deeplearning.ai/the-batch/issue-284/</link>
      <description>The Batch AI News and Insights: Writing software, especially prototypes, is becoming cheaper. This will lead to increased demand for people who can decide what to build. AI Product Management has a bright future!</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DeepSeek’s Open Reasoning Model, Affordable Humanoid Robots, Texas’ Restrictive AI Law, GenAI for Electronics</title>
      <link>https://www.deeplearning.ai/the-batch/issue-285/</link>
      <description>The Batch AI News and Insights: Greetings from Davos, Switzerland! Many business and government leaders are gathered here again for the annual World Economic Forum to discuss tech, climate, geopolitics, and economic growth.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reinforcement Learning Heats Up, White House Orders Muscular AI Policy, Computer Use Gains Momentum, Fine Control of Fine-Tuning</title>
      <link>https://www.deeplearning.ai/the-batch/issue-286/</link>
      <description>The Batch AI News and Insights: The buzz over DeepSeek this week crystallized, for many people, a few important trends that have been happening in plain sight.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>o3-mini Puts Reasoning in High Gear, How to Train for Computer Use, Gemini 2.0 Thinks Faster, More-Responsive Voice Interactions</title>
      <link>https://www.deeplearning.ai/the-batch/issue-287/</link>
      <description>The Batch AI News and Insights: A “10x engineer” — a widely accepted concept in tech — purportedly has 10 times the impact of the average engineer.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>OpenAI Does Deep Research, Google Goes to War, Alibaba Answers DeepSeek, Web Agents Do Tree Search</title>
      <link>https://www.deeplearning.ai/the-batch/issue-288/</link>
      <description>The Batch AI News and Insights: At the Artificial Intelligence Action Summit in Paris this week, U.S. Vice President J.D. Vance said, “I’m not here to talk about AI safety.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Grok 3 Scales Up, Mobile Apps Generated To Order, Musk Moves On OpenAI, Officials Reverse Course on AI Regulation</title>
      <link>https://www.deeplearning.ai/the-batch/issue-289/</link>
      <description>The Batch AI News and Insights: Last month, a drone from Skyfire AI was credited with saving a police officer’s life after a dramatic 2 a.m. traffic stop.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Meta Reads Minds, Big AI Spending Climbs, Deepfakes Appropriate Celeb Likenesses, Reasoning in Vectors</title>
      <link>https://www.deeplearning.ai/the-batch/issue-290/</link>
      <description>The Batch AI News and Insights: The Voice Stack is improving rapidly. Systems that interact with users via speaking and listening will drive many new applications.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GPT-4.5 Goes Big, Claude 3.7 Reasons, Alexa+ Goes Agentic, Generating Text Like an Image</title>
      <link>https://www.deeplearning.ai/the-batch/issue-291/</link>
      <description>The Batch AI News and Insights: Continuing our discussion on the Voice Stack, I’d like to explore an area that today’s voice-based systems mostly struggle with: Voice Activity Detection (VAD) and the turn-taking paradigm of communication.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DeepSeek-R1 Uncensored, QwQ-32B Puts Reasoning in Smaller Model, Phi-4-multimodal Takes Spoken Input, Training AI May Not Be Fair Use</title>
      <link>https://www.deeplearning.ai/the-batch/tag/mar-12-2025/</link>
      <description>The Batch AI News and Insights: Some people today are discouraging others from learning programming on the grounds AI will automate it.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
