<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>projectdiscovery</title>
    <link>https://projectdiscovery.io/blog</link>
    <description>Latest posts from https://projectdiscovery.io/blog. follow.is: None</description>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <generator>python-feedgen</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 02 Mar 2025 01:42:13 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <title>Engineering the future of vulnerability detection</title>
      <link>https://projectdiscovery.io/blog/engineering-the-future-of-vulnerability-detection</link>
      <description>We’re building the future of Nuclei-powered scanning - 35x faster, with automated scheduling, smart alerts, and streamlined triaging. With built-in internal scanning, it’s designed for modern security teams who need speed, scale, and precision.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reinventing custom detections and vulnerability management</title>
      <link>https://projectdiscovery.io/blog/reinventing-custom-detections-and-vulnerability-management</link>
      <description>We’re making custom vulnerability detection easier with an AI-powered template editor, full-text search, and auto-regressions. These additions help security teams create, refine, and validate detections faster, staying ahead of threats with less manual work.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>February 2025 Newsletter</title>
      <link>https://projectdiscovery.io/blog/february-2025-newsletter</link>
      <description>First, we’re so excited to announce that we’ve reached 100,000 GitHub stars across our OSS projects! This wouldn’t have been possible without everyone who’s contributed, used our tools, and offered their support along the way. Thank you, and we can’t wait to keep building with you! 🎉</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Getting Started with ProjectDiscovery in Linux and Windows</title>
      <link>https://projectdiscovery.io/blog/getting-started-with-projectdiscovery-in-linux-and-windows</link>
      <description>"Just for you, we’ve got this brand new blog all about getting started with ProjectDiscovery on Linux AND Windows."</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bug Bounty Etiquette: More than Ethical Hacking (part one)</title>
      <link>https://projectdiscovery.io/blog/bug-bounty-etiquette-more-than-ethical-hacking-part-one</link>
      <description>This is part one of our two-part series on polite hacking, focusing on what to do. Part two talks about what not to do (link coming soon). 

This blog is not about techniques. It’s not about tools to use, how to find the vulnerability, or anything like that. There are plenty of those out there. It’s much more like an etiquette guide for Bug Bounty reporting, and how working within these social norms can lead to better outcomes for you in your career! Think of it like a cotillion class, or the fa</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bug Bounty Etiquette: Our Guide to Polite Hacking (Part Two)</title>
      <link>https://projectdiscovery.io/blog/bug-bounty-etiquette-2-what-not-to-do</link>
      <description>This is the second part of our series on bug bounty etiquette. Part one looks at what you should be doing. 

Last month we talked about bug bounty etiquette and how to be a good bug bounty hunter; not in the sense of finding more bugs, but rather in how to be the kind of bug bounty hunter people want to work with. This time, we have some advice about what NOT to while bug bounty hunting. Let's get started.

 1. Don’t go all out
 2. Don’t ignore the rules
 3. Don’t report unnecessary stuff
 4. Do</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nuclei v3.2 Release with Authenticated Scanning, Advanced Fuzzing &amp; more</title>
      <link>https://projectdiscovery.io/blog/nuclei-3-2</link>
      <description>We're thrilled to announce the launch of Nuclei v3.2.0. This latest version introduces a host of new features, enhancements, and bug fixes, significantly elevating the Nuclei engine's performance and capabilities. Notably, the inclusion of authentication support and advanced fuzzing support positions this release as a pivotal milestone, further building upon the foundation laid by version 3.0.0.

In this blog, and a number of upcoming feature spotlights, you'll learn a lot more about all that nu</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enhancing Asset Discovery: ProjectDiscovery Cloud Platform (v0.8.8)</title>
      <link>https://projectdiscovery.io/blog/pdcp-0-8-8</link>
      <description>We're excited to announce the release of version 0.8.8 of the ProjectDiscovery Cloud Platform. This update brings significant enhancements to our asset discovery capabilities, introduces new features for Basic Tier (Free) users, and resolves several critical issues. Our primary focus remains on improving the visibility and analysis of discovered assets and refining the insights available to our users.


Empowering Basic Tier (Free) Users

Our mission at ProjectDiscovery is to make advanced secur</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Advancing Asset Management - PDCP v0.8.9</title>
      <link>https://projectdiscovery.io/blog/advancing-asset-management-pdcp-v0-8-9-2</link>
      <description>We're excited to announce the release of version 0.8.9 of the ProjectDiscovery Cloud Platform. This update introduces significant enhancements to our asset management capabilities, focusing on asset inventory, AI-powered search, and improved user experience.


Key Features in v0.8.9


Asset Inventory and Technologies

The new interface for cataloging and organizing all assets along with their associated technologies in one place represents a significant advancement in asset management. Now, rega</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Alibaba Cloud - Nuclei Templates v10.1.1 🎉</title>
      <link>https://projectdiscovery.io/blog/alibaba-cloud-nuclei-templates-v10-1-1-2</link>
      <description>We're excited to tell you about Nuclei Templates release v10.1.1 ! This new version includes newly added Alibaba Cloud Review templates. In this blog post, we'll discuss automating Alibaba cloud misconfiguration review, creating custom checks, and sharing results on the PDCP Cloud for review.

An Alibaba Cloud Configuration Security Review is essential for assessing and improving the security of your cloud infrastructure. It ensures that your resources are configured correctly, compliant with re</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Crafting DAST Nuclei Templates for OOB Template Engines Injection: A Practical Guide</title>
      <link>https://projectdiscovery.io/blog/crafting-dast-nuclei-templates-for-oob-template-engines-injection-a-practical-guide</link>
      <description>We’re thrilled to announce the release of new DAST Out-of-Band Template Injection Templates tailored for various templating engines and programming frameworks. This update empowers us to assess vulnerabilities and misconfigurations in diverse tech stacks effectively. In this post, we’ll explore automating Out-of-Band Template Injection Testing, crafting custom vulnerability checks, and sharing the findings through the PDCP Cloud for streamlined collaboration.

For those particularly interested i</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Effortless Passive Detection Using Global Matchers in Nuclei</title>
      <link>https://projectdiscovery.io/blog/introducing-global-matchers-in-nuclei</link>
      <description>If you've ever found yourself repeatedly setting up the same matchers in multiple Nuclei templates, it's time to break free from that cycle. Meet global matchers, a killer feature in Nuclei that simplifies your detection workflow.

Imagine having a single template that automatically hunts for specific patterns (like private keys, sensitive tokens, or webhooks) across every HTTP response from all your other templates. That's what global matchers do — and they do it effortlessly.

In this post, we</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ruby-SAML / GitLab Authentication Bypass (CVE-2024-45409)</title>
      <link>https://projectdiscovery.io/blog/ruby-saml-gitlab-auth-bypass</link>
      <description>Introduction

In this blog post, we will analyze CVE-2024-45409, a critical vulnerability impacting Ruby-SAML, OmniAuth-SAML libraries, which effectively affects GitLab. This vulnerability allows an attacker to bypass SAML authentication mechanisms and gain unauthorized access by exploiting a flaw in how SAML responses are handled. The issue arises due to weaknesses in the verification of the digital signature used to protect SAML assertions, allowing attackers to manipulate the SAML response a</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GitHub Enterprise SAML Authentication Bypass (CVE-2024-4985 / CVE-2024-9487)</title>
      <link>https://projectdiscovery.io/blog/github-enterprise-saml-authentication-bypass</link>
      <description>Introduction

In light of the recent Ruby-SAML bypass discovered in GitLab, we set out to examine the SAML implementation within GitHub Enterprise. During our research, we identified a significant vulnerability that enabled bypassing GitHub’s SAML authentication when encrypted assertions were in use.

This blog post will provide an in-depth look at GitHub Enterprise’s SAML implementation and analyze the specific code issue that permitted this bypass. Although we uncovered this vulnerability inde</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DeepSeek’s Data Breach: Could ProjectDiscovery’s Cloud Have Prevented the Hack?</title>
      <link>https://projectdiscovery.io/blog/deepseeks-data-breach-could-projectdiscoverys-cloud-have-prevented-the-hack-2</link>
      <description>Last week, DeepSeek made headlines with R1, an open-source model positioned as a competitor to OpenAI’s Model o1. What set R1 apart wasn’t just its capabilities - it was the claim that DeepSeek trained it with significantly fewer GPUs. It challenged conventional wisdom around the compute requirements for large-scale model training and even caused a small stock market selloff.

Amid the hype, a security incident surfaced: researchers gained access to DeepSeek’s internal databases. The breach repo</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The new way to discover your exposure</title>
      <link>https://projectdiscovery.io/blog/the-new-way-to-discover-your-exposure</link>
      <description>We've completely rebuilt our infrastructure for exposure discovery and management at the internet level, introducing new tools and AI workflows. This major update is designed for our entire community - from individual users to large security teams.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scaling for the enterprise</title>
      <link>https://projectdiscovery.io/blog/scaling-for-the-enterprise</link>
      <description>Large organizations manage a complex web of internet exposures, spanning subsidiaries, multi-cloud environments, and distributed deployments. Security teams need visibility, collaboration, and control to manage their digital footprint at scale.

With this launch, we’re introducing a suite of new enterprise-focused features: an improved free experience, streamlined onboarding, advanced reporting, and essential controls like SAML SSO and audit logs. These updates make it easier for enterprises to</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Engineering the future of vulnerability detection</title>
      <link>https://projectdiscovery.io/blog/engineering-the-future-of-vulnerability-detection</link>
      <description>We’re building the future of Nuclei-powered scanning - 35x faster, with automated scheduling, smart alerts, and streamlined triaging. With built-in internal scanning, it’s designed for modern security teams who need speed, scale, and precision.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
