<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>rapid7_blog</title>
    <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/posts/</link>
    <description>Latest posts from https://www.rapid7.com/blog/posts/. follow.is: feedId:71371191432910863+userId:71370844472670208</description>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <generator>python-feedgen</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 19 Dec 2024 01:39:40 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <title>Metasploit Weekly Wrap-Up 11/29/2024</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2024/11/29/metasploit-weekly-wrapup-11-29-2024/</link>
      <description>Four new Metasploit modules released, including CUPS IPP Attributes LAN Remote Code Execution CVE-2024-47176</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Why Cybercriminals Are Not Necessarily Embracing AI</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2024/12/02/why-cybercriminals-are-not-necessarily-embracing-ai/</link>
      <description>The rapid advancement of AI has offered powerful tools for malware detection, but it has also introduced new avenues for adversarial attacks.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Expanded SOC Coverage Into AWS Environments with Rapid7 MXDR</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2024/12/03/expanded-soc-coverage-into-aws-environments-with-rapid7-mxdr/</link>
      <description>With Rapid7’s Managed Extended Detection and Response (MXDR) service, organizations can confidently scale their cloud investments without sacrificing the comprehensive coverage they’re familiar with today.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lorex 2K Indoor Wi-Fi Security Camera: Multiple Vulnerabilities (FIXED)</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2024/12/03/lorex-2k-indoor-wi-fi-security-camera-multiple-vulnerabilities-fixed/</link>
      <description>The Lorex 2K Indoor Wi-Fi Security Camera is a consumer security device that provides cloud-based video camera surveillance capabilities. This device was a target at the 2024 Pwn2Own IoT competition. As of December 3, 2024, we are disclosing these issues publicly in coordination with the vendor.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Black Basta Ransomware Campaign Drops Zbot, DarkGate, and Custom Malware</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2024/12/04/black-basta-ransomware-campaign-drops-zbot-darkgate-and-custom-malware/</link>
      <description>Beginning in early October, Rapid7 has observed a resurgence of activity related to the ongoing social engineering campaign being conducted by Black Basta ransomware operators.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rapid7 Extends Cloud Security Capabilities with Updates to Exposure Command</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2024/12/06/rapid7-extends-cloud-security-capabilities-with-updates-to-exposure-command/</link>
      <description>With purpose-built harvesting technology providing real-time visibility into everything running across multi-cloud environments, Exposure Command from Rapid7 ensures teams have an up-to-date inventory, mapping their cloud attack surface and enriching asset data with risk and business context.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Metasploit Weekly Wrap-Up 12/06/2024</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2024/12/06/metasploit-weekly-wrap-up-44/</link>
      <description>Post-Thanksgiving Big Release
This week's release is an impressive one. It adds 9 new modules, which will get
you remote code execution on products such as Ivanti Connect Secure, VMware
vCenter Server, Asterisk, Fortinet FortiManager and Acronis Cyber Protect. It
also includes an account takeover on Wordpress, a local privilege escalation on
Windows and a X11 keylogger module. Finally, this release improves the
fingerprinting logic for the TeamCity login module and adds instructions about
the in</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Widespread Exploitation of Cleo File Transfer Software (CVE-2024-55956)</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2024/12/10/etr-widespread-exploitation-of-cleo-file-transfer-software-cve-2024-50623/</link>
      <description>On Monday, December 9, multiple security firms began privately circulating
reports of in-the-wild exploitation targeting Cleo file transfer software. Late
the evening of December 9, security firm Huntress published a blog
 
on active exploitation of three different Cleo products (docs

):

 *</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Patch Tuesday - December 2024</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2024/12/10/patch-tuesday-december-2024/</link>
      <description>1 zero-day. CLFS EoP. 16 critical RCEs. Hyper-V container escape. Multiple Remote Desktop Services RCE.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modular Java Backdoor Dropped in Cleo Exploitation Campaign</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2024/12/11/etr-modular-java-backdoor-dropped-in-cleo-exploitation-campaign/</link>
      <description>While investigating incidents related to Cleo software exploitation, Rapid7 Labs and MDR team discovered a novel, multi-stage attack that deploys an encoded Java Archive (JAR) payload.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Navigating Choppy Waters: Top Security Predictions from Rapid7's 2025 Webinar</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2024/12/12/navigating-choppy-waters-top-security-predictions-from-rapid7s-2025-webinar/</link>
      <description>Hosted by industry heavy hitter Brian Honan, CEO of BH Consulting, the webinar brought together Rapid7 security and policy experts Raj Samani, Chief Scientist, and Sabeen Malik, VP of Global Government Affairs and Public Policy.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Metasploit Weekly Wrap-Up 12/13/2024</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2024/12/13/metasploit-weekly-wrap-up-12-13-2024/</link>
      <description>It’s raining RCEs!
It's the second week of December and the weather forecast announced another
storm of RCEs in Metasploit-Framework land. This weekly release includes RCEs
for Moodle e-Learning platform, Primefaces, WordPress Really Simple SSL and
CyberPanel along with two modules to change password through LDAP and SMB
protocol.

New module content (7)
Change Password
Author: smashery
Type: Auxiliary
Pull request: #19671  
contributed</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2024 Threat Landscape Statistics: Ransomware Activity, Vulnerability Exploits, and Attack Trends</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2024/12/16/2024-threat-landscape-statistics-ransomware-activity-vulnerability-exploits-and-attack-trends/</link>
      <description>In this blog, the global experts across our Rapid7 Labs and Managed Services teams share real-time vulnerability insights and threat intelligence so that our customers can anticipate and prevent breaches, pinpoint critical threats, and confidently take command of their attack surface.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Take Command of Your Career: Practicing Self-Advocacy as a Woman in Tech</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2024/12/17/take-command-of-your-career-practicing-self-advocacy-as-a-woman-in-tech/</link>
      <description>As the year draws to a close, it’s essential—and often expected—to reflect on our achievements and lessons learned in preparation for annual performance reviews and setting future goals.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What’s New in Rapid7 Products &amp; Services: Q4 2024 in Review</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2024/12/18/whats-new-in-rapid7-products-services-q4-2024-in-review/</link>
      <description>Below, we’ve highlighted key releases and updates from the quarter across our products and services, including the new Platform Home Navigation experience, extensibility enhancements to Exposure Command and Surface Command, expanded MXDR support, and 2024 threat landscape trends from Rapid7 Labs.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
