<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>rapid7_blog</title>
    <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/posts/</link>
    <description>Latest posts from https://www.rapid7.com/blog/posts/. follow.is: feedId:71371191432910863+userId:71370844472670208</description>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <generator>python-feedgen</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 23 Feb 2025 01:39:55 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <title>Excellence in Leadership: CRN Recognizes Alex Page Among Its 2025 Channel Chiefs</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2025/02/03/excellence-in-leadership-crn-recognizes-alex-page-among-its-2025-channel-chiefs/</link>
      <description>For the third consecutive year, Rapid7’s Alex Page has been honored as a CRN Channel Chief, a testament to his unwavering commitment to driving growth, fostering innovation, and strengthening our global channel partnerships.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Introducing the Exposure Management Webinar Series: Commanding Your Attack Surface</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2025/02/04/introducing-the-exposure-management-webinar-series-commanding-your-attack-surface/</link>
      <description>The digital landscape is expanding rapidly, and with it, the complexity of managing an organization's attack surface. To help cybersecurity professionals navigate this challenge, Rapid7 presents a three-part webinar series, "Commanding Your Attack Surface."</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Take Command | Rapid7’s 2025 Cybersecurity Summit: Own Your Attack Surface on April 9</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2025/02/05/take-command-rapid7s-2025-cybersecurity-summit/</link>
      <description>Take Command is back. After a hugely successful event last year, Rapid7’s cybersecurity summit returns with another stellar lineup to equip security teams with the latest threat intelligence, expert insights, and real-world strategies to take control of an evolving attack landscape.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>4 Reasons Why MSPs &amp; MSSPs Need to Enhance Attack Surface Management</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2025/02/06/4-reasons-why-msps-and-mssps-need-attack-surface-management/</link>
      <description>Here are four key reasons why enhancing attack surface management should be a top priority for MSPs and MSSPs.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Metasploit Weekly Wrap-Up 02/07/2025</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2025/02/07/metasploit-weekly-wrap-up-02-07-2025/</link>
      <description>Gathering data and improving workflows
This week's release includes 2 new auxiliary modules targeting Argus
Surveillance DVR and Ivanti Connect Secure. The former, contributed by Maxwell
Francis, and based on the work of John Page, can be used to retrieve arbitrary
files on the target's filesystem by exploiting an unauthenticated directory
traversal vulnerability. The latter, brought by our very own Martin Šutovský
, is a HTTP login scanner for Ivanti Connect
Sec</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vector Command Opportunistic Phishing Blog</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2025/02/07/vector-command-opportunistic-phishing-blog/</link>
      <description>Vector Command is Rapid7’s new continuous red teaming managed service, designed to  assess your external attack surface and identify gaps in the security defenses on an ongoing basis.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interning at Rapid7 Prague: Meet Mko</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2025/02/10/interning-at-rapid7-prague-meet-mko/</link>
      <description>Mkrtich Hovsepyan – most people call him Mko –  is an intern at Rapid7’s fast-growing office in Prague. He was in our first impressive crop of interns, and is sharing his experience as we gear up for our next wave of intern hiring.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How To Protect Your Organization's Bluesky Account From Security Threats</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2025/02/11/how-to-protect-your-organizations-bluesky-account-from-security-threats/</link>
      <description>This blog explains how to secure your Bluesky account from security threats such as malware and phishing, as well as establishing your identity to help prevent fraud and impersonation.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Patch Tuesday - February 2025</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2025/02/11/microsoft-patch-tuesday/</link>
      <description>Four zero-days: AFD EoP, Storage EoP, NTLMv2 disclosure, Surface container escape. Critical RCEs in LDAP, DHCP client, Excel.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CVE-2025-1094: PostgreSQL psql SQL injection (FIXED)</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2025/02/13/cve-2025-1094-postgresql-psql-sql-injection-fixed/</link>
      <description>Rapid7 discovered and is disclosing CVE-2025-1094, a high-severity SQL injection vulnerability affecting the PostgreSQL interactive tool psql.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Xerox Versalink C7025 Multifunction Printer: Pass-Back Attack Vulnerabilities (FIXED)</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2025/02/14/xerox-versalink-c7025-multifunction-printer-pass-back-attack-vulnerabilities-fixed/</link>
      <description>During security testing, Rapid7 discovered that Xerox Versalink C7025 Multifunction printers (MFPs) were vulnerable to pass-back attacks.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Metasploit Weekly Wrap-Up 02/14/2025</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2025/02/14/metasploit-weekly-wrap-up-45/</link>
      <description>New module content (2)
Unauthenticated RCE in NetAlertX
Authors: Chebuya (Rhino Security Labs) and Takahiro Yokoyama
Type: Exploit
Pull request: #19868  
contributed by Takahiro-Yoko 
Path: linux/http/netalertx_rce_cve_2024_46506
AttackerKB reference: CVE-2024-46506


Description: A new module for an unauthenticated remote code execution bug i</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rapid7 Fills Gaps in the CVE Assessment Process with AI-Generated Vulnerability Scoring in Exposure Command</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2025/02/19/rapid7-fills-gaps-in-the-cve-assessment-process-with-ai-generated-vulnerability-scoring-in-exposure-command/</link>
      <description>To address this widening gap in vulnerability scoring and ensure our customers are making informed decisions with the most accurate understanding of their current risk posture we’re excited to announce the release of AI-Generated Risk Scoring in Exposure Command.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Take Command | Rapid7’s 2025 Cybersecurity Summit: First Look at Our Speaker Lineup</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2025/02/19/take-command-rapid7s-2025-cybersecurity-summit-first-look-at-our-speaker-lineup/</link>
      <description>Take Command Summit 2025 takes place on April 9, 2025, as a fully virtual, one-day event. Don’t miss the opportunity to hear from industry leaders, engage with Rapid7 experts, and walk away with actionable security strategies.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Metasploit Weekly Wrap-Up 02/21/2025</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2025/02/21/metasploit-weekly-wrap-up-46/</link>
      <description>BeyondTrust exploit + fetch payload updates
This Metasploit release includes an exploit module that chains two
vulnerabilities, one exploited in the wild by APT groups and another one, a
0-day discovered by Rapid7
 during
the vulnerability analysis. This week's release also includes a significant
enhancement to Metasploit's fetch payloads, which now support PPC, MIPS and ARM 
architectures. This allows the payloads to be use</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
