<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>rapid7_blog</title>
    <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/posts/</link>
    <description>Latest posts from https://www.rapid7.com/blog/posts/. follow.is: feedId:71371191432910863+userId:71370844472670208</description>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <generator>python-feedgen</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 10 Jan 2025 01:36:39 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <title>Widespread Exploitation of Cleo File Transfer Software (CVE-2024-55956)</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2024/12/10/etr-widespread-exploitation-of-cleo-file-transfer-software-cve-2024-50623/</link>
      <description>On Monday, December 9, multiple security firms began privately circulating
reports of in-the-wild exploitation targeting Cleo file transfer software. Late
the evening of December 9, security firm Huntress published a blog
 
on active exploitation of three different Cleo products (docs

):

 *</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Patch Tuesday - December 2024</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2024/12/10/patch-tuesday-december-2024/</link>
      <description>1 zero-day. CLFS EoP. 16 critical RCEs. Hyper-V container escape. Multiple Remote Desktop Services RCE.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modular Java Backdoor Dropped in Cleo Exploitation Campaign</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2024/12/11/etr-modular-java-backdoor-dropped-in-cleo-exploitation-campaign/</link>
      <description>While investigating incidents related to Cleo software exploitation, Rapid7 Labs and MDR team discovered a novel, multi-stage attack that deploys an encoded Java Archive (JAR) payload.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Navigating Choppy Waters: Top Security Predictions from Rapid7's 2025 Webinar</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2024/12/12/navigating-choppy-waters-top-security-predictions-from-rapid7s-2025-webinar/</link>
      <description>Hosted by industry heavy hitter Brian Honan, CEO of BH Consulting, the webinar brought together Rapid7 security and policy experts Raj Samani, Chief Scientist, and Sabeen Malik, VP of Global Government Affairs and Public Policy.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Metasploit Weekly Wrap-Up 12/13/2024</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2024/12/13/metasploit-weekly-wrap-up-12-13-2024/</link>
      <description>It’s raining RCEs!
It's the second week of December and the weather forecast announced another
storm of RCEs in Metasploit-Framework land. This weekly release includes RCEs
for Moodle e-Learning platform, Primefaces, WordPress Really Simple SSL and
CyberPanel along with two modules to change password through LDAP and SMB
protocol.

New module content (7)
Change Password
Author: smashery
Type: Auxiliary
Pull request: #19671  
contributed</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2024 Threat Landscape Statistics: Ransomware Activity, Vulnerability Exploits, and Attack Trends</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2024/12/16/2024-threat-landscape-statistics-ransomware-activity-vulnerability-exploits-and-attack-trends/</link>
      <description>In this blog, the global experts across our Rapid7 Labs and Managed Services teams share real-time vulnerability insights and threat intelligence so that our customers can anticipate and prevent breaches, pinpoint critical threats, and confidently take command of their attack surface.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Take Command of Your Career: Practicing Self-Advocacy as a Woman in Tech</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2024/12/17/take-command-of-your-career-practicing-self-advocacy-as-a-woman-in-tech/</link>
      <description>As the year draws to a close, it’s essential—and often expected—to reflect on our achievements and lessons learned in preparation for annual performance reviews and setting future goals.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What’s New in Rapid7 Products &amp; Services: Q4 2024 in Review</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2024/12/18/whats-new-in-rapid7-products-services-q4-2024-in-review/</link>
      <description>Below, we’ve highlighted key releases and updates from the quarter across our products and services, including the new Platform Home Navigation experience, extensibility enhancements to Exposure Command and Surface Command, expanded MXDR support, and 2024 threat landscape trends from Rapid7 Labs.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Metasploit Weekly Wrap-Up 12/20/2024</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2024/12/20/metasploit-weekly-wrap-up-12-20-2024/</link>
      <description>New module content (4)
GameOver(lay) Privilege Escalation and Container Escape
Authors: bwatters-r7, g1vi, gardnerapp, and h00die
Type: Exploit
Pull request: #19460  
contributed by gardnerapp 
Path: linux/local/gameoverlay_privesc
AttackerKB reference: CVE-2023-2640


Description: Adds a module for CVE-2023-2640 and CVE-2023-32629, a local
privil</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Metasploit 2024 Annual Wrap-Up</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2025/01/03/metasploit-2024-annual-wrap-up/</link>
      <description>Another year has come and gone, and the Metasploit team has taken some time to
review the year’s notable additions. This year saw some great new features
added, Metasploit 6.4 released
 
and a slew of new modules. We’re grateful to the community members new and old
that have submitted modules and issues this year. The real privilege escalation
was the privilege of working with the contributors and friends we made alo</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Out With the Old, In With the New: Securely Disposing of Smart Devices</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2025/01/06/out-with-the-old-in-with-the-new-securely-disposing-of-smart-devices/</link>
      <description>Hopefully you received some cool smart technology, or maybe you just upgraded your smart camera or voice assistant to a newer model or version. If you upgraded to a new model or version, what is your plan for the old device? Is it still working or is it broken?</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rapid7 Recognized with Top Score of 100 in 2025 Corporate Equality Index</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2025/01/07/rapid7-recognized-with-top-score-of-100-in-2025-corporate-equality-index/</link>
      <description>On January 7, the Human Rights Campaign Foundation released their 2025 Corporate Equality Index (CEI), where Rapid7 earned a top score of 100.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CVE-2025-0282: Ivanti Connect Secure zero-day exploited in the wild</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2025/01/08/etr-cve-2025-0282-ivanti-connect-secure-zero-day-exploited-in-the-wild/</link>
      <description>Two stack-based buffer overflow issues were disclosed in Ivanti Connect Secure, Policy Secure, and Neurons for ZTA. CVE-2025-0282, the more severe of the two issues, has been exploited in the wild against Ivanti Connect Secure devices.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New Research: Enhancing Botnet Detection with AI using LLMs and Similarity Search</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2025/01/08/new-research-enhancing-botnet-detection-with-ai-using-llms-and-similarity-search/</link>
      <description>As botnets continue to evolve, so do the techniques required to detect them.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Built In Honors Rapid7 with “2025 Best Places To Work” Award</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2025/01/09/built-in-honors-rapid7-with-2025-best-places-to-work-award/</link>
      <description>3 Rapid7 Offices Included in Built In’s “Best Places to Work” Lists.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
