<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>rapid7_blog</title>
    <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/posts/</link>
    <description>Latest posts from https://www.rapid7.com/blog/posts/. follow.is: feedId:71371191432910863+userId:71370844472670208</description>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <generator>python-feedgen</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 01:43:33 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <title>Unlock 24/7 SOC Coverage: Rapid7 MXDR Now Supports with Microsoft Security Products</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2024/11/18/unlock-24-7-soc-coverage-rapid7-mxdr-now-supports-with-microsoft-security-products/</link>
      <description>With the launch of Rapid7 MXDR’s SOC support for key Microsoft security products, we’re making it possible for organizations to layer security defenses and amplify outcomes.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Accelerate Mean Time to Exposure Remediation Across Hybrid Environments with Remediation Hub</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2024/11/19/accelerate-mean-time-to-exposure-remediation-across-hybrid-environments-with-remediation-hub/</link>
      <description>Rapid7’s Remediation Hub, our newest addition to the Exposure Command platform. Remediation Hub automatically prioritizes various risk signals across your hybrid environment and suggests the actions your team can take that would have the largest impact on reducing your overall risk posture.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rapid7 Recognized for ‘Excellence in Workplace Health and Wellbeing’ at the Belfast Telegraph IT Awards</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2024/11/19/rapid7-recognized-for-excellence-in-workplace-health-and-wellbeing-at-the-belfast-telegraph-it-awards/</link>
      <description>On Friday, November 15th, Rapid7 was awarded ‘Excellence in Workplace Health and Wellbeing’ at the Belfast Telegraph IT Awards. This award recognizes technology companies in Belfast that prioritize employee well-being.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rapid7 Extends AWS Support to Include Coverage for Newly-Launched Resource Control Policies (RCPs)</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2024/11/20/rapid7-extends-aws-support-to-include-coverage-for-newly-launched-resource-control-policies-rcps/</link>
      <description>Rapid7 is excited to announce our support for Amazon Web Services’ (AWS) new Resource Control Policies (RCPs), a powerful tool designed to bolster security controls for organizations using AWS infrastructure.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multiple Vulnerabilities in Wowza Streaming Engine (Fixed)</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2024/11/20/multiple-vulnerabilities-in-wowza-streaming-engine-fixed/</link>
      <description>Rapid7 is disclosing multiple vulnerabilities in Wowza Streaming Engine below v4.9.1. These vulnerabilities are tracked as CVE-2024-52052, CVE-2024-52053, CVE-2024-52054, CVE-2024-52055, and CVE-2024-52056. They are patched as of Wowza Streaming Engine v4.9.1.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Bag of RATs: VenomRAT vs. AsyncRAT</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2024/11/21/a-bag-of-rats-venomrat-vs-asyncrat/</link>
      <description>Remote access tools (RATs) have long been a favorite tool for cyber attackers, since they enable remote control over compromised systems and facilitate data theft, espionage, and continuous monitoring of victims. Among the well-known RATs are VenomRAT and AsyncRAT.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Metasploit Weekly Wrap-Up 11/22/2024</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2024/11/22/metasploit-weekly-wrap-up-11-22-2024/</link>
      <description>JetBrains TeamCity Login Scanner
Metasploit added a login scanner for the TeamCity application to enable users to
check for weak credentials. TeamCity has been the subject of multiple ETR
vulnerabilities
 
and is a valuable target for attackers.

Targeted DCSync added to Windows Secrets Dump
This week, Metasploit community member smashery</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New “CleverSoar” Installer Targets Chinese and Vietnamese Users</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2024/11/27/new-cleversoar-installer-targets-chinese-and-vietnamese-users/</link>
      <description>In early November, Rapid7 Labs identified a new, highly evasive malware installer, 'CleverSoar,' targeting Chinese and Vietnamese-speaking victims.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Metasploit Weekly Wrap-Up 11/29/2024</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2024/11/29/metasploit-weekly-wrapup-11-29-2024/</link>
      <description>Four new Metasploit modules released, including CUPS IPP Attributes LAN Remote Code Execution CVE-2024-47176</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Why Cybercriminals Are Not Necessarily Embracing AI</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2024/12/02/why-cybercriminals-are-not-necessarily-embracing-ai/</link>
      <description>The rapid advancement of AI has offered powerful tools for malware detection, but it has also introduced new avenues for adversarial attacks.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Expanded SOC Coverage Into AWS Environments with Rapid7 MXDR</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2024/12/03/expanded-soc-coverage-into-aws-environments-with-rapid7-mxdr/</link>
      <description>With Rapid7’s Managed Extended Detection and Response (MXDR) service, organizations can confidently scale their cloud investments without sacrificing the comprehensive coverage they’re familiar with today.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lorex 2K Indoor Wi-Fi Security Camera: Multiple Vulnerabilities (FIXED)</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2024/12/03/lorex-2k-indoor-wi-fi-security-camera-multiple-vulnerabilities-fixed/</link>
      <description>The Lorex 2K Indoor Wi-Fi Security Camera is a consumer security device that provides cloud-based video camera surveillance capabilities. This device was a target at the 2024 Pwn2Own IoT competition. As of December 3, 2024, we are disclosing these issues publicly in coordination with the vendor.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Black Basta Ransomware Campaign Drops Zbot, DarkGate, and Custom Malware</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2024/12/04/black-basta-ransomware-campaign-drops-zbot-darkgate-and-custom-malware/</link>
      <description>Beginning in early October, Rapid7 has observed a resurgence of activity related to the ongoing social engineering campaign being conducted by Black Basta ransomware operators.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rapid7 Extends Cloud Security Capabilities with Updates to Exposure Command</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2024/12/06/rapid7-extends-cloud-security-capabilities-with-updates-to-exposure-command/</link>
      <description>With purpose-built harvesting technology providing real-time visibility into everything running across multi-cloud environments, Exposure Command from Rapid7 ensures teams have an up-to-date inventory, mapping their cloud attack surface and enriching asset data with risk and business context.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Metasploit Weekly Wrap-Up 12/06/2024</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2024/12/06/metasploit-weekly-wrap-up-44/</link>
      <description>Post-Thanksgiving Big Release
This week's release is an impressive one. It adds 9 new modules, which will get
you remote code execution on products such as Ivanti Connect Secure, VMware
vCenter Server, Asterisk, Fortinet FortiManager and Acronis Cyber Protect. It
also includes an account takeover on Wordpress, a local privilege escalation on
Windows and a X11 keylogger module. Finally, this release improves the
fingerprinting logic for the TeamCity login module and adds instructions about
the in</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
