<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>rapid7_blog</title>
    <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/posts/</link>
    <description>Latest posts from https://www.rapid7.com/blog/posts/. follow.is: feedId:71371191432910863+userId:71370844472670208</description>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <generator>python-feedgen</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 07 Feb 2025 01:26:33 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <title>Metasploit Wrap-Up 01/10/2025</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2025/01/10/metasploit-wrap-up-01-10-2025/</link>
      <description>New module content (5)
OneDev Unauthenticated Arbitrary File Read
Authors: Siebene and vultza
Type: Auxiliary
Pull request: #19614  
contributed by vultza 
Path: gather/onedev_arbitrary_file_read
AttackerKB reference: CVE-2024-45309


Description: This adds an exploit module for an unauthenticated arbitrary file
read vulnerability, tracked as CVE-202</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Patch Tuesday - January 2025</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2025/01/14/patch-tuesday-january-2025/</link>
      <description>Eight 0-days. Access: triple zero-day RCE; Hyper-V NT Kernel Integration VSP: triple zero-day EoP; Windows Themes: zero-day NTLM disclosure; Windows Installer: zero-day EoP; PGM: critical RCE; OLE: critical RCE.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fortinet Firewalls Hit with New Zero-Day Attack, Older Data Leak</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2025/01/16/etr-fortinet-firewalls-hit-with-new-zero-day-attack-older-data-leak/</link>
      <description>Rapid7 is responding to two separate events affecting Fortinet firewall customers: Zero-day exploitation of CVE-2024-55591 in FortiOS, and a large-scale data leak of older FortiGate firewall IPs, passwords, and configs.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Perfect Fit or Business Threat? How to Mitigate the Risk of Rogue Employees</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2025/01/16/perfect-fit-or-business-threat-how-to-mitigate-the-risk-of-rogue-employees/</link>
      <description>Recruitment fraud is an expensive and time-consuming threat to business. The risk of malware deployment and data exfiltration is high from threat actors trained to bypass each stage of a typical recruitment process. This blog outlines how an organization can secure the hiring process weak points.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Metasploit Wrap-Up 01/17/2025</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2025/01/17/metasploit-wrap-up-01-17-2025/</link>
      <description>Three new Metasploit exploit modules released, including a module targeting Cleo File Transfer Software (CVE-2024-55956)</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Key Takeaways: Mastering Risk Prioritization with Rapid7 Surface Command</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2025/01/23/key-takeaways-mastering-risk-prioritization-with-rapid7-surface-command/</link>
      <description>In our recent webinar, Cheney Edwards, Senior Security Solutions Engineer at Rapid7, shares actionable techniques to cut through noise, prioritize effectively, and command your attack surface.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Vulnerability Vortex: Escaping the Whirlpool of Ineffective Security</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2025/01/24/the-vulnerability-vortex-escaping-the-whirlpool-of-ineffective-security/</link>
      <description>In today's interconnected digital landscape, organizations find themselves caught in a relentless torrent of security alerts and vulnerability notifications.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Metasploit Weekly Wrap-Up 01/24/2025</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2025/01/24/metasploit-weekly-wrap-up-01-24-2025/</link>
      <description>LibreNMS Authenticated RCE module and ESC15 improvements
This week the Metasploit Framework was blessed with an authenticated RCE module
in LibreNMS, an autodiscovering PHP/MySQL-based network monitoring system. An
authenticated attacker can create dangerous directory names on the system and
alter sensitive configuration parameters through the web portal. These two
defects combined to allow arbitrary OS commands inside shell_exec() calls, thus
achieving arbitrary code execution.

Additionally, i</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The 2024 Ransomware Landscape: Looking back on another painful year</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2025/01/27/the-2024-ransomware-landscape-looking-back-on-another-painful-year/</link>
      <description>In this post, we’ll examine the latest data points, discuss notable groups, and estimate the potential impact on victims — helping security teams plan their defenses for the months ahead.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Paying It Forward: Giving and Receiving Mentorship in Tech</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2025/01/30/paying-it-forward-giving-and-receiving-mentorship-in-tech/</link>
      <description>This post was adapted from the Northern Ireland Developer Conference 2024 talk of the same name.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Metasploit Weekly Wrap-Up 01/31/25</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2025/01/31/metasploit-weekly-wrap-up-01-31-25/</link>
      <description>ESC4 Detection
This week, Metasploit’s jheysel-r7  updated the
existing ldap_esc_vulnerable_cert_finder module to include detecting template
objects that can be written to by the authenticated user. This means the module
can now identify instances of ESC4 from the perspective of the account that the
Metasploit operator provided the credentials for. Metasploit has been capable of
exploiting ESC4 for some time, but required users to know which certificate
templates t</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Excellence in Leadership: CRN Recognizes Alex Page Among Its 2025 Channel Chiefs</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2025/02/03/excellence-in-leadership-crn-recognizes-alex-page-among-its-2025-channel-chiefs/</link>
      <description>For the third consecutive year, Rapid7’s Alex Page has been honored as a CRN Channel Chief, a testament to his unwavering commitment to driving growth, fostering innovation, and strengthening our global channel partnerships.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Introducing the Exposure Management Webinar Series: Commanding Your Attack Surface</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2025/02/04/introducing-the-exposure-management-webinar-series-commanding-your-attack-surface/</link>
      <description>The digital landscape is expanding rapidly, and with it, the complexity of managing an organization's attack surface. To help cybersecurity professionals navigate this challenge, Rapid7 presents a three-part webinar series, "Commanding Your Attack Surface."</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Take Command | Rapid7’s 2025 Cybersecurity Summit: Own Your Attack Surface on April 9</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2025/02/05/take-command-rapid7s-2025-cybersecurity-summit/</link>
      <description>Take Command is back. After a hugely successful event last year, Rapid7’s cybersecurity summit returns with another stellar lineup to equip security teams with the latest threat intelligence, expert insights, and real-world strategies to take control of an evolving attack landscape.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>4 Reasons Why MSPs &amp; MSSPs Need to Enhance Attack Surface Management</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2025/02/06/4-reasons-why-msps-and-mssps-need-attack-surface-management/</link>
      <description>Here are four key reasons why enhancing attack surface management should be a top priority for MSPs and MSSPs.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
