<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>rapid7_blog</title>
    <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/posts/</link>
    <description>Latest posts from https://www.rapid7.com/blog/posts/. follow.is: feedId:71371191432910863+userId:71370844472670208</description>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <generator>python-feedgen</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 01:41:47 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <title>Command Platform Innovations Eliminate Data Blind Spots Through Complete Visibility and Context-Driven Risk Prioritization</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2025/02/25/command-platform-innovations-eliminate-data-blind-spots-through-complete-visibility-and-context-driven-risk-prioritization/</link>
      <description>Sensitive Data Discovery in Exposure Command delivers continuous visibility into sensitive data across multicloud environments, ensuring that security teams can proactively protect high-value assets.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Uncovering and Protecting Sensitive Data Across Cloud Environments with Exposure Command</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2025/02/25/uncovering-and-protecting-sensitive-data-across-cloud-environments-with-exposure-command/</link>
      <description>This enhancement enables organizations to centralize sensitive data insights across their cloud environments, providing a unified view of data risks and exposures.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MDR + SIEM: Why Full Access to Your Security Logs is Non-Negotiable</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2025/02/26/mdr-siem-why-full-access-to-your-security-logs-is-non-negotiable/</link>
      <description>Pairing MDR with a Security Information and Event Management (SIEM) solution ensures complete transparency, enabling real-time investigation, historical threat hunting, compliance readiness, and deeper threat insights.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Why MDR In 2025 Is About Scaling With Purpose</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2025/02/27/why-mdr-in-2025-is-about-scaling-with-purpose/</link>
      <description>Forrester recently released “The Forrester Wave™: Managed Detection and Response (MDR) Services, Q1 2025,", highlighting the top 10 MDR providers out of more than 600 worldwide.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Metasploit Weekly Wrap-Up: 02/28/2025</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2025/02/28/metasploit-weekly-wrap-up-02-28-2025/</link>
      <description>New module content (5)
mySCADA myPRO Manager Credential Harvester (CVE-2025-24865 and CVE-2025-22896)
Author: Michael Heinzl
Type: Auxiliary
Pull request: #19878  
contributed by h4x-x0r 
Path: admin/scada/mypro_mgr_creds
AttackerKB reference: CVE-2025-22896


Description: This module adds credential harvesting for MySCADA MyPro Manager
using CVE-20</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Building a High Performance Team in India: Meet Swami Nathan</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2025/03/04/building-a-high-performance-team-in-india-meet-swami-nathan/</link>
      <description>Swami Nathan has a track record of building new teams from scratch for global companies. Through his experiences, he’s identified what it takes to build not just any team, but a high performing team that drives innovation for business while propelling career trajectories for those who take the ride.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multiple Zero-Day Vulnerabilities in Broadcom VMware ESXi and Other Products</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2025/03/04/etr-multiple-zero-day-vulnerabilities-in-broadcom-vmware-esxi-and-other-products/</link>
      <description>On Tuesday, March 4, 2025, Broadcom published a critical security advisory (VMSA-2025-0004) on 3 new zero-day vulnerabilities affecting multiple VMware products, including ESXi, Workstation, and Fusion.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inside the Take Command Summit 2025 Agenda: What’s in Store for This Year’s Event?</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2025/03/05/inside-the-take-command-summit-2025-agenda-whats-in-store-for-this-years-event/</link>
      <description>Join Take Command 2025, a free virtual cybersecurity event on April 9. Hear from industry experts on AI-driven security, real-world attack simulations, and frontline SOC threat hunting strategies. Register now!</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Metasploit Wrap-Up 03/06/2025</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2025/03/06/metasploit-wrap-up-03-06-2025/</link>
      <description>New module content (3)
Get NAA Credentials
Authors: skelsec, smashery, and xpn
Type: Auxiliary
Pull request: #19712  
contributed by smashery 
Path: admin/sccm/get_naa_credentials

Description: Adds an auxiliary module which performs the retrieval of Network
Access Account (NAA) credentials from an System Center Configuration Manager
(SCCM) server. Given a computer name and password (which can typically be
cr</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Seeing The Whole Picture: A Better Way To Manage Your Attack Surface</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2025/03/10/seeing-the-whole-picture-a-better-way-to-manage-your-attack-surface/</link>
      <description>With cloud adoption, remote work, shadow IT, and AI, security teams face an overwhelming challenge: scoping their attack surface and continuously discovering all assets and exposures before threats emerge.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Helping us help you: Practical applications of AI in the SOC</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2025/03/11/helping-us-help-you-practical-applications-of-ai-in-the-soc/</link>
      <description>Whether or not you're a customer of Rapid7’s managed security offerings, it's worth understanding how AI is already transforming security operations today – not as a vague promise of the future, but as a real, tangible advantage in the fight against cyber threats.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Patch Tuesday - March 2025</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2025/03/11/patch-tuesday-march-2025/</link>
      <description>Seven zero-days. Win32 EoP. Multiple filesystem driver attacks. MMC security feature bypass. Access (again). WSL magic email RCE. Malicious RDP server.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Explaining External Network Assessment with Vector Command</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2025/03/12/explaining-external-network-assessment-with-vector-command/</link>
      <description>Learn how external network assessment works within Vector Command, Rapid7’s continuous red team managed service.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unlocking MSSP Success: Why CTEM is Critical</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2025/03/14/unlocking-mssp-success-why-ctem-is-critical/</link>
      <description>Discover why Continuous Threat Exposure Management (CTEM) is a game-changer for MSSPs. Learn how a proactive, risk-based security approach helps service providers stand out, reduce exposure, and deliver measurable security improvements.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Metasploit Weekly Wrap-Up 03/14/25</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2025/03/14/metasploit-weekly-wrap-up-03-14-25/</link>
      <description>New module content (1)
InvoiceShelf unauthenticated PHP Deserialization Vulnerability
Authors: Mickaël Benassouli, Rémi Matasse, and h00die-gr3y

Type: Exploit
Pull request: #19950  
contributed by h00die-gr3y 
Path: linux/http/invoiceshelf_unauth_rce_cve_2024_55556
AttackerKB reference: CVE-2024-55556


Descripti</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
