<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>rapid7_blog</title>
    <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/posts/</link>
    <description>Latest posts from https://www.rapid7.com/blog/posts/. follow.is: feedId:71371191432910863+userId:71370844472670208</description>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <generator>python-feedgen</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 30 Nov 2024 01:37:57 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <title>Metasploit Wrap-Up: 11/08/2024</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2024/11/08/metasploit-wrap-up-11-08-2024/</link>
      <description>RISC-V Support
This release of Metasploit Framework has added exciting new features such as new
payloads that target the RISC-V architecture. These payloads allow for the
execution of commands on compromised hardware, allowing Metasploit Framework and
Metasploit Payloads to be used in more environments.

SMB To HTTP(S) Relay
This new exploit worked on by Rapid7 contributors targets the ESC8
vulnerability. This work is a part of the recent Kerberos and Active Directory
efforts targeting multiple</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LodaRAT: Established Malware, New Victim Patterns</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2024/11/12/lodarat-established-malware-new-victim-patterns/</link>
      <description>Rapid7 has observed an ongoing malware campaign involving a new version of LodaRAT. This version possesses the ability to steal cookies and passwords from Microsoft Edge and Brave.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Patch Tuesday - November 2024</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2024/11/12/patch-tuesday-november-2024/</link>
      <description>4 zero-days. AD CS ESC15 aka EKUwu. NTLMv2 disclosure. Exchange sender spoofing. Task scheduler EoP. .NET &amp; Kerberos critical RCEs. Welcome Server 2025.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Zero-Day Exploitation Targeting Palo Alto Networks Firewall Management Interfaces</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2024/11/15/etr-zero-day-exploitation-targeting-palo-alto-networks-firewall-management-interfaces/</link>
      <description>Palo Alto Networks has indicated they are observing threat activity exploiting a zero-day unauthenticated remote command execution vulnerability in their firewall management interfaces.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New IDR Log Search Enhancements: Accelerate, Streamline, and Simplify Investigations</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2024/11/15/new-idr-log-search-enhancements-accelerate-streamline-and-simplify-investigations/</link>
      <description>Rapid7’s InsightIDR, the foundation of our Managed Detection and Response (MDR) service, empowers security teams with advanced analytics, automation, and expert-led investigations.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Metasploit Weekly Wrap-Up: 11/15/2024</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2024/11/15/metasploit-weekly-wrap-up-43/</link>
      <description>Palo Alto Expedition RCE module
This week's release includes an exploit module for the Palo Alto Expedition
exploit chain that's been making headlines recently. The first vulnerability,
CVE-2024-5910, allows attackers to reset the password of the admin user. The
second vulnerability, CVE-2024-9464 is an authenticated OS command injection.
The module makes use of both vulnerabilities in order to obtain unauthenticated
RCE in the context of the user www-data.

New module content (1)
Palo Alto Expe</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unlock 24/7 SOC Coverage: Rapid7 MXDR Now Supports with Microsoft Security Products</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2024/11/18/unlock-24-7-soc-coverage-rapid7-mxdr-now-supports-with-microsoft-security-products/</link>
      <description>With the launch of Rapid7 MXDR’s SOC support for key Microsoft security products, we’re making it possible for organizations to layer security defenses and amplify outcomes.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Accelerate Mean Time to Exposure Remediation Across Hybrid Environments with Remediation Hub</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2024/11/19/accelerate-mean-time-to-exposure-remediation-across-hybrid-environments-with-remediation-hub/</link>
      <description>Rapid7’s Remediation Hub, our newest addition to the Exposure Command platform. Remediation Hub automatically prioritizes various risk signals across your hybrid environment and suggests the actions your team can take that would have the largest impact on reducing your overall risk posture.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rapid7 Recognized for ‘Excellence in Workplace Health and Wellbeing’ at the Belfast Telegraph IT Awards</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2024/11/19/rapid7-recognized-for-excellence-in-workplace-health-and-wellbeing-at-the-belfast-telegraph-it-awards/</link>
      <description>On Friday, November 15th, Rapid7 was awarded ‘Excellence in Workplace Health and Wellbeing’ at the Belfast Telegraph IT Awards. This award recognizes technology companies in Belfast that prioritize employee well-being.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rapid7 Extends AWS Support to Include Coverage for Newly-Launched Resource Control Policies (RCPs)</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2024/11/20/rapid7-extends-aws-support-to-include-coverage-for-newly-launched-resource-control-policies-rcps/</link>
      <description>Rapid7 is excited to announce our support for Amazon Web Services’ (AWS) new Resource Control Policies (RCPs), a powerful tool designed to bolster security controls for organizations using AWS infrastructure.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multiple Vulnerabilities in Wowza Streaming Engine (Fixed)</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2024/11/20/multiple-vulnerabilities-in-wowza-streaming-engine-fixed/</link>
      <description>Rapid7 is disclosing multiple vulnerabilities in Wowza Streaming Engine below v4.9.1. These vulnerabilities are tracked as CVE-2024-52052, CVE-2024-52053, CVE-2024-52054, CVE-2024-52055, and CVE-2024-52056. They are patched as of Wowza Streaming Engine v4.9.1.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Bag of RATs: VenomRAT vs. AsyncRAT</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2024/11/21/a-bag-of-rats-venomrat-vs-asyncrat/</link>
      <description>Remote access tools (RATs) have long been a favorite tool for cyber attackers, since they enable remote control over compromised systems and facilitate data theft, espionage, and continuous monitoring of victims. Among the well-known RATs are VenomRAT and AsyncRAT.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Metasploit Weekly Wrap-Up 11/22/2024</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2024/11/22/metasploit-weekly-wrap-up-11-22-2024/</link>
      <description>JetBrains TeamCity Login Scanner
Metasploit added a login scanner for the TeamCity application to enable users to
check for weak credentials. TeamCity has been the subject of multiple ETR
vulnerabilities
 
and is a valuable target for attackers.

Targeted DCSync added to Windows Secrets Dump
This week, Metasploit community member smashery</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New “CleverSoar” Installer Targets Chinese and Vietnamese Users</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2024/11/27/new-cleversoar-installer-targets-chinese-and-vietnamese-users/</link>
      <description>In early November, Rapid7 Labs identified a new, highly evasive malware installer, 'CleverSoar,' targeting Chinese and Vietnamese-speaking victims.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Metasploit Weekly Wrap-up 11/29/2024</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2024/11/29/metasploit-weekly-wrapup-11-29-2024/</link>
      <description>Four new Metasploit modules released, including CUPS IPP Attributes LAN Remote Code Execution CVE-2024-47176</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
