<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>rapid7_blog</title>
    <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/tag/research/</link>
    <description>Latest posts from https://www.rapid7.com/blog/tag/research/</description>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <generator>python-feedgen</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 10:25:04 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <title>Whispers of Atlantida: Safeguarding Your Digital Treasure</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2024/01/17/whispers-of-atlantida-safeguarding-your-digital-treasure/</link>
      <description>Recently, Rapid7 observed a new stealer named Atlantida. The stealer tricks users to download a malicious file from a compromised website, and uses several evasion techniques such as reflective loading and injection before the stealer is loaded.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Critical CVEs in Outdated Versions of Atlassian Confluence and VMware vCenter Server</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2024/01/19/etr-critical-cves-in-outdated-versions-of-atlassian-confluence-and-vmware-vcenter-server/</link>
      <description>Rapid7 is highlighting two critical vulnerabilities in outdated versions of
widely deployed software this week. Atlassian disclosed
[https://confluence.atlassian.com/security/cve-2023-22527-rce-remote-code-execution-vulnerability-in-confluence-data-center-and-confluence-server-1333990257.html] 
CVE-2023-22527, a template injection vulnerability in Confluence Server with a
maxed-out CVSS score of 10, while VMware pushed a fresh update to its October
2023 vCenter Server advisory
[https://www.vmwar</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CVE-2024-0204: Critical Authentication Bypass in Fortra GoAnywhere MFT</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2024/01/23/etr-cve-2024-0204-critical-authentication-bypass-in-fortra-goanywhere-mft/</link>
      <description>On January 22, 2024, Fortra published a security advisory on CVE-2024-0204, a critical authentication bypass affecting its GoAnywhere MFT secure managed file transfer product prior to version 7.4.1.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exploring the (Not So) Secret Code of Black Hunt Ransomware</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2024/02/05/exploring-the-not-so-secret-code-of-blackhunt-ransomware-2/</link>
      <description>In this analysis we examined the BlackHunt sample shared on X (formerly Twitter). During our analysis we found notable similarities between BlackHunt ransomware and LockBit, which suggested that it uses leaked code of Lockbit. In addition, it uses some techniques similar to REvil ransomware.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Critical Fortinet FortiOS CVE-2024-21762 Exploited</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2024/02/12/etr-critical-fortinet-fortios-cve-2024-21762-exploited/</link>
      <description>CVE-2024-21762 is a critical out-of-bounds write vulnerability in Fortinet's FortiOS operating system that is known to have been exploited in the wild. Fortinet SSL VPN vulnerabilities are frequent targets for state-sponsored and other motivated adversaries.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RCE to Sliver: IR Tales from the Field</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2024/02/15/rce-to-sliver-ir-tales-from-the-field/</link>
      <description>Rapid7 Incident Response was engaged to investigate an incident involving unauthorized access to two publicly-facing Confluence servers that were the source of multiple malware executions.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High-Risk Vulnerabilities in ConnectWise ScreenConnect</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2024/02/20/etr-high-risk-vulnerabilities-in-connectwise-screenconnect/</link>
      <description>On February 19, 2024 ConnectWise disclosed two vulnerabilities in their ScreenConnect remote access software. Both vulnerabilities affect ScreenConnect 23.9.7 and earlier.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CVE-2024-27198 and CVE-2024-27199: JetBrains TeamCity Multiple Authentication Bypass Vulnerabilities (FIXED)</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2024/03/04/etr-cve-2024-27198-and-cve-2024-27199-jetbrains-teamcity-multiple-authentication-bypass-vulnerabilities-fixed/</link>
      <description>Rapid7’s vulnerability research team identified two new vulnerabilities affecting JetBrains TeamCity CI/CD server: CVE-2024-27198 and CVE-2024-27199, both of which are authentication bypasses.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Updated APT Playbook: Tales from the Kimsuky threat actor group</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2024/03/20/the-updated-apt-playbook-tales-from-the-kimsuky-threat-actor-group/</link>
      <description>Within Rapid7 Labs we continually track and monitor threat groups. As part of this process, we routinely identify evolving tactics from threat groups in what is an unceasing game of cat and mouse.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Why The External Attack Surface Matters: An analysis into APAC related threat activities</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2024/03/21/why-the-external-attack-surface-matters-an-analysis-into-apac-related-threat-activities/</link>
      <description>Considerable focus within the cybersecurity industry has been placed on the attack surface of organizations, giving rise to external attack surface management (EASM) technologies as a means to monitor said surface.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stories from the SOC Part 2: MSIX Installer Utilizes Telegram Bot to Execute IDAT Loader</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2024/04/10/stories-from-the-soc-part-2-msix-installer-utilizes-telegram-bot-to-execute-idat-loader/</link>
      <description>In part one of our blog series, we discussed how a Rust based application was used to download and execute the IDAT Loader. In part two of this series, we will be providing analysis of how an MSIX installer led to the download and execution of the IDAT Loader.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rapid7 Releases the 2024 Attack Intelligence Report</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2024/05/21/rapid7-releases-the-2024-attack-intelligence-report/</link>
      <description>Today, during our Take Command Summit, we released our 2024 Attack Intelligence
Report, which pulls in expertise from our researchers, our detection and
response teams, and threat intelligence teams. The result is the clearest
picture yet of the expanding attack surface
[https://www.rapid7.com/fundamentals/attack-surface/] and the threats security
professionals face every day. 

Since the end of 2020, we’ve seen a significant increase in zero-day
exploitation, ransomware attacks, and mass compro</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Defending Against APTs: A Learning Exercise with Kimsuky</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2024/07/16/defending-against-apts-a-learning-exercise-with-kimsuky/</link>
      <description>The latest research paper coming out of Rapid7 Labs examines the tactics of North Korea’s Kimsuky threat group.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New Research: The Proliferation of Cellular in IoT</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2024/07/30/new-research-the-proliferation-of-cellular-in-iot/</link>
      <description>Analysis of Cellular Based Internet of Things (IoT) Technology is a new whitepaper co-authored by Rapid7 principal security researcher Deral Heiland and Thermo Fisher Scientific lead product security researcher Carlota Bindner.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ransomware Groups Demystified: CyberVolk Ransomware</title>
      <link>https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2024/10/03/ransomware-groups-demystified-cybervolk-ransomware/</link>
      <description>As part of our ongoing efforts to monitor emerging cyber threats, we have analyzed the activities of CyberVolk, a politically motivated hacktivist group that transitioned into using ransomware and has been active since June 2024.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
